<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/feed/writings.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-20T15:43:50+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/feed/writings.xml</id><title type="html">Junk Drawer | Writings</title><subtitle>For all those little papers scattered across your desk</subtitle><author><name>benknoble</name></author><entry><title type="html">PCM Sunday Sermon</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/pcm_sunday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PCM Sunday Sermon" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/pcm_sunday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/pcm_sunday/"><![CDATA[<p>My friends and I have this wacky tradition—we call it “Spot your
Doppelgänger.” We all have people on campus that look just enough like us to be
confusing, and we make a game out of finding them. I, miraculously, have yet to
find my campus Doppelgänger—but when we started talking about these texts and
themes with John, I discovered my biblical Doppelgänger.</p>

<p>I last read David’s Psalm 139 with PCM during our annual Fall Retreat, and I
remember being overwhelmed by the emotion gripping David. David doesn’t say, “I
am the king.” David doesn’t say, “I am great.” David says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If I say, “Surely the darkness will hide me and the light become night around
me,” even the darkness will not be dark to you (Psalm 139: 11–12)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>David is battered by shame and doubt. David is trying to hide from God! David,
in the words of Lisa Sharon Harper, was an “unlikely leader,” “a confessed
adulterer,” “rapist,” and “murderer.” This is a “far cry” from the “shalom” God
is calling us to. David’s self-image is so worn down that he struggles to
recognized God’s pure, perfect love. This is not new to me: friends, this is the
image of my biblical Doppelgänger. Covered in shame, hiding from my own self and
from vulnerability with others, I know what is to be like the deeply sinful
David. David struggled. So do I. And don’t we all?</p>

<p>I would like to share with you my response to Psalm 139, written at Fall
Retreat; you will find it in your bulletin if you would like to follow along.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Shattered,
Scattered
  a million stars.
Knit together,
Whole,
  on earth a single sun—
  on earth a single son.

Broken body,
Broken heart,
Broken soul—

Heal me;
Mend me;
Draw me into you.

Tear down my walls.
Redeem my fear and my failures.
Throw back my cloak of truth and lies—
Unmask my scarred face.

Clip the strings of my control.

Swim through me.
Dance with me.
Sing, cry, shout with me.

Clench your fist—
  make your palms bleed
       your knuckles raw.

Unwind, loosen, detach—
  breathe with me;
  feel your lungs expand, contract;
  rest your eyes.
Push out—dispel evil.
Pull in—consecrate me.

Be still and know me.
Be still and let me
             see you
             hear you
             know you.

Please?
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Friends, I have some good news and some challenging news for all of us.</p>

<p>The good new is that God loves us all right to the core of our beings, and we
were made for shalom, peace, and love with ourselves as part of our relationship
with God. Harper says “Every relationship created by God is strung together in a
web of intimate relationships.” The tapestry of our relationships is beautiful,
and that includes our relationships with ourselves, and with others, and with
our God.</p>

<p>This is good. This brings me hope in my shame.</p>

<p>But there is a challenge here. Harper cites researcher Brené Brown as saying
“Shame is a social concept—it happens between people—it also heals best
between people.” In many ways, this is great news! There is nothing inherently
wrong with us. Made in the image and likeness of God, our natural state does
<em>not</em> include shame. Instead, our natural state is <em>relationship with God</em>. But
this news is also a challenge: to confront my shame, I need people. And for
others to confront theirs, they need me. This is a necessary and desirable
vulnerability, and yet it is scary.</p>

<p>Not one of us <em>wants</em> to be so weak and so broken that we need a savior to love
us and redeem us the way Jesus does. But aren’t we all? As we move into the
Lenten season this week, I would encourage each of us to think about our need
for a restorative savior, one who brings shalom and without whom we cannot be
whole. How can we listen to God’s voice over the voice of our shame?</p>

<p>So I leave you with this: who helps you confront your shame? Who lifts up the
Lord’s love for you? And how can you do that for others?</p>

<p>Said another way: How are each of us rejoicing in the shalom of Eden but
mourning its loss? How are each of us the woman at the well, thirsting for a
living water? And how are each of us David, drowning in shame and longing for
the restorative shalom with ourselves?</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My friends and I have this wacky tradition—we call it “Spot your Doppelgänger.” We all have people on campus that look just enough like us to be confusing, and we make a game out of finding them. I, miraculously, have yet to find my campus Doppelgänger—but when we started talking about these texts and themes with John, I discovered my biblical Doppelgänger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BS/MS Personal Statement—Right Brain, Left Brain</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/bsms-statement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BS/MS Personal Statement—Right Brain, Left Brain" /><published>2019-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/bsms-statement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/bsms-statement/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>The limits of my language mean the limits of my world.</p>

  <p>—Ludwig Wittgenstein [1]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My life experiences have led me to conclude that everything we experience,
create, and do in our lives both produces, and is a product of, language. From
programming to playing an instrument, from math to martial arts, we simply
cannot escape the structure of languages, the specialized notations, the
all-senses-engaged nature of communication. Contrary to my introverted
tendencies, humans—myself included—rely on and thrive on communication. Below, I
explain how my conception of language as a unifying tool drives my desire to
participate in the B.S./M.S. combined program.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Vigorous writing is concise. This requires that every word tell.</p>

  <p>—adapted from William Strunk, Jr. [2]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Putting the fun back in hacking!</p>

  <p>—Cynbe, author of Mythryl, a Standard Meta Language fork [3]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Just as vigorous writing is concise, so must vigorous programming be concise.
Strunk eloquently states that this does not require arcane, unreadable syntaxes;
rather, it requires that each language construct is adequately expressive, both
to reader and writer. I discovered my passion for concisely expressive
writing—code or otherwise— through many papers, through projects in Compilers,
and through my time on Piazza as both student and Learning Assistant. In
particular, this sort of construction relies on knowing the right language for
the (programming) job. For example, while I coordinate processes in shell, I
work with mathematical definitions in Scala, and I write a French paper in
French. For me, the essence of Cynbe’s slogan for Mythryl is this passion: I
love the many programming languages, and I love to program languages.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The difference between the right word and the almost right word is really a
large matter—’tis the difference between the lightning-bug and the lightning.</p>

  <p>—Mark Twain [4]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>How do we teach the “right words” of computer science (CS)? Talks by Colleen
Lewis, CS pedagogy researcher at Harvey Mudd College, led me to see the profound
need for more intuitive programming models. To close the gap between Twain’s
“lightning” and “lightning-bug,” between pointers and programs, between objects
and big-O notation, between functional programming and fun programming—this is
my goal as a future M.S. student and future educator (for any expert in a field
ultimately must educate in some form). Our languages must reflect our realities.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A language that doesn’t affect the way you think about programming is not worth knowing.</p>

  <p>—Alan Perlis [5]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The world needs capable CS experts to translate our domain language to a broader
context. Consider the Facebook scandals, exposing a need for the General Data
Protection Regulation and digital privacy. Or consider DeepFake, revealing a
need for trustworthy digital content policy. There is thus a need for
independent, unbiased experts who understand and translate these issues. How can
nations and peoples make good decisions without appropriate subject-matter
knowledge? David Auerbach, in his 2018 memoir <em>Bitwise: A Life in Code</em>, details
how the digital controls and classifies the human [6]. He claims that digital
algorithms over-simplify and over-categorize our behaviors while driving
behavior into the same categories. For our own sake, we must not over-simplify
the computer case, but we must ensure that those making decisions have the
appropriate information.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Will felt that the reader was in serious trouble most of the time, floundering
in a swamp, and that it was the duty of anyone attempting to write English to
drain the swamp quickly and get the reader up on dry ground, or at least to
throw a rope.</p>

  <p>—E. B. White [2]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ultimately, my passion is learning, evolving my language and expanding my limits
of the world. In doing so, I strive to become a guide and “poet” at the
intersection of bits and “thought-stuff,” much as Fred Brooks, Jr. characterizes
the work of computer scientists [7]. I hope to contribute to programming
languages that guide us towards program correctness and expressiveness. I desire
to teach languages that guide developing scientists towards robust intuition and
understanding alongside inclusive and welcoming discourse. I aim to be a part of
an expert language and community that guides both my own decisions and those of
humankind, as we seek to re-examine ourselves in this digital age. I believe
that the B.S./M.S. combined program provides me the best opportunity for
education so that I may pursue these goals and best contribute to a broader
wealth of linguistic and scientific evolution.</p>

<hr />

<p>References</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wittgentstein, Ludwig. <em>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus.</em>
<a href="">https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Tractatus_Logico-Philosophicus</a>. Accessed
17th September 2019.</li>
  <li>Strunk, William Jr. and E. B. White. <em>The Elements of Style, 4th Edition.</em>
Pearson Education, Inc.</li>
  <li>Cynbe. Mythryl. <a href="">https://mythryl.org/index3.html</a>. Accessed 17th September
2019.</li>
  <li>Twain, Mark. <em>The Wit and Wisdom of Mark Twain: A Book of Quotations.</em> Dover
Thrift Editions, 1998.</li>
  <li>Perlis, Alan. <em>Epigrams in Programming.</em>
<a href="">http://www.cs.yale.edu/homes/perlis-alan/quotes.html</a>. Accessed 17th
September 2019.</li>
  <li>Auerbach, David. <em>Bitwise: A Life in Code.</em> Pantheon Books, 2018.</li>
  <li>Brooks, Fred, Jr. <em>The Mythical Man-Month: Essays on Software Engineering.</em>
Addison-Wesley, 1995.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The limits of my language mean the limits of my world. —Ludwig Wittgenstein [1]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poem—Reactions to Psalm 139</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/139/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poem—Reactions to Psalm 139" /><published>2019-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/139</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/139/"><![CDATA[<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Shattered,
Scattered
  a million stars.
Knit together,
Whole,
  on earth a single sun—
  on earth a single son.

Broken body,
Broken heart,
Broken soul—

Heal me;
Mend me;
Draw me into you.

Tear down my walls.
Redeem my fear and my failures.
Throw back my cloak of truth and lies—
Unmask my scarred face.

Clip the strings of my control.

Swim through me.
Dance with me.
Sing, cry, shout with me.

Clench your fist—
  make your palms bleed
       your knuckles raw.

Unwind, loosen, detach—
  breathe with me;
  feel your lungs expand, contract;
  rest your eyes.
Push out—dispel evil.
Pull in—consecrate me.

Be still and know me.
Be still and let me
             see you
             hear you
             know you.

Please?
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[``` Shattered, Scattered a million stars. Knit together, Whole, on earth a single sun— on earth a single son.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dreamscape—You Are My Sunshine</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/sunshine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreamscape—You Are My Sunshine" /><published>2019-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/sunshine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/sunshine/"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I wrote a piece in what I now call the “Dreamscape collection,” I
imagined a world where I could fall asleep and wake up next to the ones I loved,
living out impossible dreams in my sleep. I am convinced that this was the
expression of not being able to spend peaceful nights with these loved ones… the
blissful yearning of a teenager, perhaps.</p>

<p>As time passed, form evolved, becoming letters and sagas. Each was a way for
very real characters to metaphorically process.</p>

<p>Now, I have found the one who will share all my nights. She will share my
forever. This dream is for her, my brightest and most beautiful soulmate.</p>

<hr />

<p>“I know, Mom. I see the clouds. Gonna be a nasty weekend.” Peering out the
blinds, he knew she—<em>his</em> she, not his mom—wouldn’t be able to make the
drive.  Not all the way across the state, not in this weather. He sighed. “At
least we’ll have the kitties. I love you.”</p>

<p>He said a silent prayer for her. <em>Be safe, my sunshine.</em> With the rain plinking
on the tin roof, he was fast asleep.</p>

<hr />

<p>He woke shivering, clothes and hair matted against his skin. It was like camping
in the rain without a tent: why did it have to be storming in his dreams too? He
had to find her… Oh, but he could still remember that nervous first time…</p>

<p>They had only just met that morning, really. He had been giddy all day
afterwards and would later learn that she smiled all the way home. He hadn’t
been sure sleep would come, questions rattling around in his head, everything
still new, confused, and had she maybe even flirted with him too? It had been so
long… Eventually, of course, he drifted off. And there in the Dreamscape, too
excited to sit still, he flew. Imagine his shock when he saw <em>her</em>, lying
against the grass, staring up at the sky, watching him. How could she be here?
And yet there she was.</p>

<p>It was long minutes before he could work up the nerve to come down.</p>

<p>“Um, hey. Were you watching me?”</p>

<p>“I’m not sure. Was I supposed to?”</p>

<p>Even her voice was perfectly her—this was no dream. It was definitely her,
here, in this magic. And, if he was honest, it frightened him a little. Enough
that he woke up and called his close friend, trying to come back to Earth. He
steeled himself to win her slowly, to step and step and step until maybe she
might want to be with him.</p>

<p>A few short days later, he found her in his dreams again. “Come with me,” he
said. “There’s something I need to say to you but cannot. I will show you.” So
he taught her to fly with him, and they soared up to a very special peak. Below
them, he explained, was the land of Ack. Down there, they could find a great
deal of art, if only they were patient enough. And hopefully, he said, they
would find a piece he had been searching for.</p>

<p>“What is it?”</p>

<p>“I cannot tell you. Not yet.”</p>

<p>And so they searched and searched, patiently at times, at others it seemed they
would draw so close, only to remember themselves. Neither could get a handle on
the other. Finally, though, they found the misshapen lump of red rock. “This,”
he declared. She studied it.</p>

<p>“But what is it? It rather resembles a heart…”</p>

<p><em>Indeed</em>, he thought. “What do you think it is?”</p>

<p>“Perhaps a molten, red sun. But why show me this?”</p>

<p>And so, with some prompting, he confessed he hadn’t stopped thinking about her.
Luckily for him, neither had she. And she wasn’t (to appearance) nearly so
nervous about saying it as he was.</p>

<p>That one dream had led to so many adventures, some patient, others… not so much.
They continued to meet, to love, to stare at each other when the other wasn’t
looking. The days grew longer, the nights shorter… which reminded him.  There
was no day at the moment—it was storming. He hadn’t seen it like this in
years, and even then it was usually <em>his</em> grief that affected the weather so. He
<em>had</em> to find her.</p>

<p>Find her he did, on their little island. A slice of paradise, just for them, as
he usually thought of it. Just there, a little beach cove on which they had lain
so many times. And there, in the distance, the strangely infinite mountain they
had hiked and climbed, never the same twice. Just beyond, their vegetable
garden, a sprawling, wild growth.</p>

<p>Today, though, unlike so many others, the sea churned, the sky was gray like
ash, the garden was sodden, squishy, muddy. Even the mountain looked
particularly jagged. And the incessant rain, as though the sky itself cried.</p>

<p>So did she. Alone, on a rock in the sea, battered by waves, she cried. She
screamed, large, and then shrunk in oh-so-small, unable to let anyone see her
even breathe. Shivering, she hugged herself and rocked, bare against the
weather.</p>

<p>He could just catch her soft cries: “What is wrong with me? What is wrong with
me?”</p>

<p>And so he did the only thing he knew to do: he sang.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>You are my sunshine,
my only sunshine.
You make me happy
when skies are gray.
You'll never know, dear,
how much I love you,
so please don't take my sunshine away.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It was the song of storms and sun, of mothers and children, of lovers and loved,
and it beat within him like a fiery drum. More than anything he had ever known,
this was truth. This was forever.</p>

<p>And then he scooped her into his arms and whispered, “Nothing is wrong with you.
Do you see the trees? Perfect creations. And the flowers? And the vegetables you
adore so much? And the birds and the bees and all of this world? They are
perfect creations. Not because <em>we</em> dream them, for they are beyond us. They are
perfect in their own creation. And so, my love, are you.</p>

<p>“Just as the sun shines perfectly, and the Earth is just the right tilt to have
produced you and me and the seasons and this wonderfully beautiful life, so do
you shine perfectly. Brightly. Don’t take my sunshine away.”</p>

<p>But the storm raged on, and they were swept away into the ocean.</p>

<hr />

<p>The next day, the clouds had parted. The grass glistened, wet, and the great
oaks in the yard bowed under a heavy weight. But it was true daylight: the sun
shone again. The air pressed close and warm against him, whispering, “Go… go…”
And so he got into his car and drove towards his very real sunshine, smiling
like a complete fool.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first time I wrote a piece in what I now call the “Dreamscape collection,” I imagined a world where I could fall asleep and wake up next to the ones I loved, living out impossible dreams in my sleep. I am convinced that this was the expression of not being able to spend peaceful nights with these loved ones… the blissful yearning of a teenager, perhaps.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Song—Why you gotta waste your food?</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/food/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Song—Why you gotta waste your food?" /><published>2017-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/food</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/food/"><![CDATA[<p>A parody of “Rude” about food waste. Original material by David Knoble.
Created for RYM ‘17.</p>

<hr />

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Saturday morning jumped out of bed and onto the sidewalk
Got on the bus and raced like a jet, too many blocks
Knocked on your door with forks in my hand
To ask you a question
Cause I know that you're a well-off man

Can I have a meal with you and your wife? say yes, say yes
Cause I need some food
You say I'll never eat with you but today I might die
Tough luck my friend but the answer is no!

Why you gotta waste your food?
Other people want some too!
Why you gotta waste your food?
You better eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Yeah no matter what you say
Eat all that food
Clean off that dirty plate

Why you gotta waste your food?

I hate to do this, you leave no choice
I can't watch you trash it
Pray and listen to that small voice
Leftover food bits
Or we will take away
All of that wasted food you know
You know you take from me
All you ever do is tell me no

Can I have a meal with you and your wife? say yes, say yes
Cause I need some food
You say I'll never eat with you but today I might die
Tough luck my friend but the answer's still no!

Why you gotta waste your food?
Other people want some too!
Why you gotta waste your food?
You better eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Yeah no matter what you say
Eat all that food
Clean off that dirty plate

Why you gotta waste your food?

Why you gotta waste your food?
Other people want some too!
Why you gotta waste your food?
You better eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Eat it all anyway
Eat all that food
Yeah no matter what you say
Eat all that food
Clean off that dirty plate

Why you gotta waste your food?
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A parody of “Rude” about food waste. Original material by David Knoble. Created for RYM ‘17.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Essay—Blankboards</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/blankboards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Essay—Blankboards" /><published>2017-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/blankboards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/blankboards/"><![CDATA[<p>The original posting of this material (written by me, David Knoble) can be found
<a href="https://youthmissionco.org/blankboards/">here</a>. This is the unedited copy
submitted for that post.</p>

<hr />

<p>Imagine a whiteboard. A big one, extending far beyond the limits of your sight.
Just a big ole blank white board, waiting to be filled in. Zoom out, and see all
the whiteboards, exactly the same humongous size as the first, filling up space
in a grid of colored marker and explosions of thought on erasable canvas.
Whiteboards as far as you can see, with words and symbols and blobs, some with
moving pictures, others playing music, some connected by strings of yarn and
others covered in sticky notes. And one, off in a corner, blank. A marker sits
on the tray, uncapped. But nothing is drawn.</p>

<p>I won’t say I’m used to having all the answers (we all know how feisty faith can
be), but in school I can usually sit with a difficult question and find words
from a fleshy fold of brain matter somewhere in the cavern that is my skull and
speak to the question, providing some form of answer. Sometimes that looks like
a lot of external processing (read: talking to walls and other inanimate
objects); at others, it’s headphones in and jamming out. Sometimes showers,
sometimes bike rides, sometimes staring at pine cones, sometimes lightning-quick
flashes of inspiration in class. I’ve even written all over paper on the walls.
Even with the tough questions, my brain is running full-speed most of the time,
drawing strange connections and ready as often as possible to spit back an
answer half-formed of precise thought and half of blob-like shapes and colors.
As you can imagine, whiteboards fill up fast that way.</p>

<p>I thrive on extended metaphor. My favorite way to write is to take a metaphor
and meditate on it, pursuing the fleeting images wherever they might lead me,
capturing their essence in a free-flowing dialogue of pen and paper. The idea
leads me; I do not control it. I think this is why I see connections well, why I
see whole systems and individual moving parts, why a peculiar song lyric reminds
me of a movie which in turn draws me to a book or a story of my grandfather’s.
I’m willing to let things go where they will, to spread and adapt and change to
the day, the space, the mood. Rarely is there something that leaves me entirely
speechless, without existing connections to draw on or thoughts to explore. I
know I’m young, and there is certainly a lot out there that is unfamiliar to me
firsthand. But we understand the unknown via the known—we incorporate new
knowledge in the context of older experience. In other words, we as human beings
<em>connect</em>. Everything is a network of emotional memory and half-remembered facts
and midnight-snack-induced dreams.  So when something doesn’t immediately become
a new branch of my worldview, I am reminded of how much I don’t know and how
difficult some experiences can be to incorporate. And that can be breath-taking.</p>

<p>Imagine then, my spiritual journey in Raleigh this summer. I am confronted daily
(thanks to my boss, Katherine, our agencies, and our community members) with
issues that leave me at a loss for words, poetic or otherwise. Often, I am
simply pensive, leaving the office concerned that I am “broken.” I reflect and
wonder and wait and throw spaghetti-thoughts at the wall, and it seems like
nothing sticks. For someone generally ready to reply, someone like me, it can be
frustrating. At first, it’s just a reminder that I ought to pause before
responding and organize my thoughts. Then, it begins to feel like I’m searching
a haystack for a needle. And after a while, the void really starts to feel
empty, as words like “toxic masculinity” and “welcoming spaces” bounce around
without company in the walls of my skull. My whiteboards of ideas and thoughts
and connections have remained mysteriously, frustratingly, quietly blank. And
not for lack of trying—we are pushed constantly to reflect on difficult
experiences, to ask the hard, deep questions, to find words in the deep dark
void that we call ourselves. And sometimes all we can do is sit and say, “I
don’t know.”</p>

<p>Before this summer started, I would have said that it’s alright to admit to not
knowing, that I’ve done it before and that I was comfortable not having all the
answers. And on some level, that was true: I don’t mind not knowing what dinner
would be, what class would look like in a few months, or what life would bring
in just a few short, sweet years. But I never realized I wouldn’t be comfortable
drawing a blank when faced with tougher questions of who we are and who we are
called to be, of where I might be welcome and where I might not be, of just what
social justice issues might look like. I sit and sit and sit and wait, staring
at the inner-most recesses of my brain, repeating the words over and over to
myself, hoping desperately for a bolt of connection, for anything I can draw on
as background, for even a solar wind to stir the cosmic tides and shift my
perspective. And that lonely little whiteboard, it just sits with me. Waiting on
me to pick up the marker and write <em>something</em>. It sits, blank. And so I sit,
uncomfortable, pensive, deep in the trenches of my brain, but unable to fight
off the pressing silence of thought.</p>

<p>And pre-summer me is almost right: it <em>is</em> alright to not know. It’s needed and
necessary and important and <em>healthy</em>. When was the last time I really found
myself speechless before I started at RYM? When did I last find myself wrestling
with some big question and unable to formulate the beginning of a response? When
last did I sit, wordless in the face of the universe, struggling against silence
and open to the possibility that it is beyond me?  But I am not <em>comfortable</em>
with it—it is intentionally uncomfortable space, space in which we push
ourselves to the limits and find that, with all barriers removed, we don’t know
which direction to go in. That confusion, that lack of direction, <em>that</em> is our
struggle with the unknown, with the deeper questions of faith in a modern
setting. What are we going to do?</p>

<p>I reflect on our theme for the summer of 2017, and I am reminded that even as we
are looking at creating space in our communities, we should also look inwards.
We should explore how we create internal space to wrestle and struggle and be
<em>wrong</em>, how we can as a community open up that space to asking tough questions.
We should make sure that, amidst a sea of busy thought and faithful action, in a
storm of colors and blobs and sticky notes, we leave open in a corner a
whiteboard, blank. Empty. Silent.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The original posting of this material (written by me, David Knoble) can be found here. This is the unedited copy submitted for that post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free-write—Late</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/late/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free-write—Late" /><published>2017-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/late</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/late/"><![CDATA[<p>A light blooms out of the dark. White and yellow-orange flash into existence,
spreading across the expansive void.</p>

<p>A coffee stain spreads across half-inked pages. The mug lies on its side, next
to the cracked and fallen pen.</p>

<p>A rose petal falls to the sidewalk. The rest of the blossom overlooks an empty
sidewalk at dawn.</p>

<hr />

<p>He hurried home that evening from work: he had a lot to do, a table to set,
candles to light, the works. Date night was stressful sometimes, but this one
had to be extra special, and that meant getting it ready was extra stressful. He
patted his coat walking down the side walk towards his apartment. Yes, still
there, right where he’d put it. Couldn’t lose that.</p>

<p>His key turns in the door, <em>click</em>. Briefcase in the corner, coat on the hook,
no time to take shoes off. When was she coming? <em>7?</em> Just an hour to get
everything ready… <em>breathe</em>. He could do it. It would be so worth it when she
got here.</p>

<p>Chicken in the stove, check. Vegetables roasted, just need reheating.
Silverware! He needs silverware… the drawer, just there on the left. On the
table; no, wait, tablecloth first. Where <em>was</em> that white tablecloth his mother
had given him? Upstairs closet, no. Pantry? There it is! On the table. Now the
silverware, the good stuff he’d inherited and polished meticulously the day
before. She’ll be here soon, just 45 minutes. What else…</p>

<p>Right! The dishes! Such fine china, worn with age and use, the very dishes from
his parents’ wedding. Does he put it on the table, or leave it in the kitchen to
serve her? Kitchen it is. He steps back, breathes. Very nice. He shivers; it’s
cold. That reminds him: the candles! On the table they go, a box of matches too.
Is that everything? Chicken, veggies, cake in the cupboard, champagne in the
fridge. Glasses, need glasses. There.</p>

<p>Now, he needs the romance. He hurries upstairs, 30 minutes to go. He smiles, the
flowers on his windowsill having grown since they started dating a year ago.
Now, they fill the box and remind him of those first days… but no time for
that. Got to get everything together. Shoot! He needs a thin vase. Downstairs,
cupboard—no, the other one—under the sink. There. And it needs water. 20
minutes. Upstairs again. Got to get that letter written. Is that this morning’s
coffee, or yesterdays? Can’t say, doesn’t matter. He shrugs it off and sets the
vase on the desk.</p>

<p>He picks up an old pen, his favorite, and begins the story of the day they met.
Such circumstance, such happenstance. An accidental bump, a brush of hands, and
then a look in the eyes and a conviction. This, he knew, would be her. The one
he would win forever. His hand sprawls quickly across the pages, ink pouring
out. Coffee mug spills, damn! It’s on the letter! Too late now. 5 minutes. Got
to get that rose. The pen is thrown down, cracking on the side. He takes the
second of two lone roses growing in his boxes, puts it in the vase. Hurry now,
hurry. Vase on the table. The letter! He almost forgot. Upstairs, about to get
the letter, doorbell rings. She’s here! He runs downstairs and throws the door
open: empty. Empty? The sidewalk is bare, blank…</p>

<p>He fingers the ring in his pocket, turning it restlessly. She was supposed to be
here hours ago… what happened?</p>

<p>Chest, hurts. Could she, doesn’t she? Wasn’t it love?</p>

<p>Cries, can’t stop, tears, sobs shake him.</p>

<hr />

<p>The sun rises on a sad, heartless morning.</p>

<p>A light blooms out of the dark. White and yellow-orange flash into existence,
spreading across the expansive void.</p>

<p>A coffee stain spreads across half-inked pages. The mug lies on its side, next
to the cracked and fallen pen.</p>

<p>A rose petal falls to the sidewalk. The rest of the blossom overlooks an empty
sidewalk at dawn.</p>

<p>A ring tumbles to the floor. His mother’s diamond shines brilliantly, and then
fades, forgotten in tears.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A light blooms out of the dark. White and yellow-orange flash into existence, spreading across the expansive void.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free-write—Infinite Forest</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/infinite_forest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free-write—Infinite Forest" /><published>2017-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/infinite_forest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/infinite_forest/"><![CDATA[<p>She is walking through a forest, a forest frozen in time. Red-gold leaves float
still, not fluttering as she brushes them with her hand nor stirring as the
white train of her dress drags across the ground. The sun is warm against her
bare back, exposed by the low cut of the dress. Her own golden brown tresses lay
against her back, caressed by the sunlight but dancing in no wind. The white
lace of her sleeves curve against the top of her shoulders and float down around
her wrists, widening into loose billows.</p>

<p>This is her life. She has been here, waiting, for a long time. Trapped amidst a
beautiful Fall, frozen after a joyful Summer, dreading the coming of Winter. She
drifts among the trees and the hills, blissfully relaxed and yet never quite
content. Something is missing, something unknown. She drifts, frozen in time,
never stopping. There is no day, no night. She sleeps not, eats not, and misses
not their pleasures. Without time, without change, how could she? And yet she
insists on searching, wandering aimlessly, seeking purpose, seeking that which
was lost. What could it be?</p>

<p>In the infinities of a timeless forest, there is no lack of meadows, each as
tranquilly still as the last. But this one, this one is different. It would be
pointless to speak of <em>when</em> she wanders into it; similarly, it has no <em>where</em>.
But it has a strangeness. At first, she stared at its flowers, seeing them
little, as they are the same flowers in many of the meadows. Now she circles the
edge, seeing a peculiar fraction of light, divisions in the smallest degree that
shouldn’t occur at all. A glint of red here, a flash of blue there. She spirals
slowly into the center, watching the flowers bend and distort, as though shards
in a broken mirror depended from a mobile all around her. The refraction grew
stronger as she neared the center, bright dazzling rainbows straining to leap
out of the corner of her eyes and into her reality, until when finally she there
arrived the entire forest was a broken fragment of color, an abstract prism of
sunlight.</p>

<p>And he existed.</p>

<p>There was no “before,” no “after,” no “then.” He had no history, like her, like
this place, because none here exists. If he had ever not existed, it would be
impossible to say. He exists now, and thus does in the entirety of time
contained here—that is, a single moment of forever.</p>

<p>However, he <em>is</em> different. Something about him isn’t her. He stares at her, and
sees her. Not just her surface beauty, but her inner unchanging emptiness. And
he fills her, pouring his love and his devotion into and over her, bathing her
in the water she didn’t know to miss. He finds her, and she at last him! The
fractured meadow erupts with a crash into an icy, reflective Winter, which
swiftly was blown away by Spring. They dissolve as the world around them fades,
having escaped the aimlessness of unchanging and eternal solitude. They existed
there, but <em>now</em> they live.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[She is walking through a forest, a forest frozen in time. Red-gold leaves float still, not fluttering as she brushes them with her hand nor stirring as the white train of her dress drags across the ground. The sun is warm against her bare back, exposed by the low cut of the dress. Her own golden brown tresses lay against her back, caressed by the sunlight but dancing in no wind. The white lace of her sleeves curve against the top of her shoulders and float down around her wrists, widening into loose billows.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free-write—House of Cards</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/house_of_cards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free-write—House of Cards" /><published>2017-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/house_of_cards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/house_of_cards/"><![CDATA[<p>A house. A strange house, built of cards. Ready to topple in the wind and yet
never seeming to fall. Not some childish card tower built on a coffee table, but
a true house, with wall and a roof and doors. The blue-patterned card backs
faced out towards the silent forest. On the inside, who knew what lay? No one
had ever set food inside. It was closely guarded, this house of cards, by the
superstition of old wives’ tales and an ominous “Beware” sign posted on the road
before it.</p>

<p>The once-villages in the valley nearby were now nothing more than decrepit
boards and long-forgotten dolls, laid barren by the same strange repulsion
centered on that house of cards. Something in the forest warned of a strange
presence: no animals chittered, no leaves stirred, nothing breathed. The whole
world held it’s breath in a moment of still, silent waiting. Nobody came here.</p>

<p>How do I know? What do I know of a long-forgotten, abandoned valley in a far
away land of mountains and mist? What could I know of such entrancing
nightmares… not enough, it seemed. The deepest mysteries have hearts of
impenetrable thickness, un-knowable without traveling deep inside them. I know
this house of cards, delicate and yet braced against a mountain’s thunderstorm,
guarded and yet with the door standing wide open, because once I journeyed to
its depths. Yes, I, the unlikely traveler, crept unnaturally through a forest,
afraid of my own noise. I passed the empty walls of old ruins and the relentless
stares of gnarled trees. I came to that sign, saw its warning. Dare I say I
ignored it? No, the folly. I heeded it well, and was cautious. I tread slowly,
still, a shadow of unseen clouds. I kept my eyes to the ground, never looking at
the house, avoiding its entrancing invitation. I was patient but unwavering. I
could not stop or I would be consumed by the strange power of that open door,
and I feared I might turn and run. In which direction, I could not be sure.</p>

<p>At long last, I found myself upon the doorstep of a flimsy porch. It wasn’t
inviting, not the way the door was. The porch had born the brunt of storms,
charred by lighting, molded by moisture, some of the cards bent or torn. I
forced myself onward. So close, and yet to what? What lie in the center, openly
daring intrusion and yet forbidding it? I stepped over the threshold. My eyes to
the floor, I nearly didn’t notice it until I stood in the middle of the empty
room. I was surrounded by the walls of card faces, and as they stared at me,
eyes un-moving, their hearts beat as one in a steady, age-old rhythm. I felt
drawn to them, and yet repulsed by their gaze; they implored me silently to come
no closer, to back-step and distance myself from them. But I could not—I had
dared come this far. I would find my answers, settle the mysteries.</p>

<p>I turned to examine the opposite wall, and imagine my surprise to find a solid
rock of black granite at the base of a pedestal. I can’t think to have missed
it, only that it had clearly always been there. I bent to pick it up, and felt
it faintly pulsing in my hand. Slowly, not the same as the now-increased tempo
of the heart-walls. It was faint. So easily missed. But I knew it, I knew it in
my heart of hearts, in the soul that beckons to the sky and the earth and
demands the million other living things know its vibrant colors, in the gut that
drops like a small, solid rock. And I could do only one thing—I engulfed it in
the love I sought for myself, and I was overcome.</p>

<p>What came next, how can I hope to describe? The cards flew apart, finally gusted
in by the wind, perhaps, the sun shone down on a forest that hadn’t known life
in aeons, and a brilliant chorus of birds erupted into the sky, singing an
ancient song in time with the beat of that stone—that red stone! No longer
black, it shone a deep red, a pulsing heart, beckoning to the life all around
it. And I, I was captivated by it. I thought to put it on the pedestal, but why?
Was it so perfect that it should be put on display and guarded by a flimsy house
of paper? No, see, it is chipped, just at the top. It has other scars, invisible
fault lines that I have found in my many hours spent with it. But that gives it
the beauty, not that silly “eye of the beholder” nonsense, that
all-encompassing, all-enrapturing beauty. The beauty the world over recognizes
for a split-second reflected back at them in those rare moments of piercing
sight that all too quickly disappears. And that beauty, that I took from the now
alive forest, and I returned to my house of cards. I tore down the walls and
rebuilt them with stone, painted them a bright red. I built a wide porch, and a
rocking chair. And I sit there now most days, rocking with my worn and chipped
heart, and I smile. I lose myself inside it’s crevasses and the contours of its
surface. As for my valley? Bathed red in a sunset unmatched save in Eden, it
flourishes.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A house. A strange house, built of cards. Ready to topple in the wind and yet never seeming to fall. Not some childish card tower built on a coffee table, but a true house, with wall and a roof and doors. The blue-patterned card backs faced out towards the silent forest. On the inside, who knew what lay? No one had ever set food inside. It was closely guarded, this house of cards, by the superstition of old wives’ tales and an ominous “Beware” sign posted on the road before it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dreamscape—Reflections</title><link href="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreamscape—Reflections" /><published>2016-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://benknoble.github.io/writings/reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://benknoble.github.io/writings/reflections/"><![CDATA[<p>Another piece for a close friend.</p>

<hr />

<p>Dark. Everything was dark. Shadows of trees rushed by, silhouetted against the
gray night sky. The usual forest scents were smothered, the expected twitters,
chirps, and rustles muffled. Layers of dead leaves littered the forest floor,
but nothing crunched in them. His footsteps as he ran made no sound—the effect
was ghostly. And the dark gray air turned everything colorless and shadowed.
What should have been a summer day filled with the blonde and gold hues of
dappled sunlight was instead transformed into an emptiness made cold by the
vacuum of emotion pulling on the ghosted fragments of what used to be.</p>

<p>She trotted through the forest on the back of a white-maned horse, his muzzle
covered in hints of ice. Frosted air streamed out of his nostrils as he gently
carried her through a world untouched by anything. She looked around curiously,
wondering what could have happened here to turn it so barren. Her slightly
curled hair dropped around her, caressing her body. Clearly, it had once been a
rich brown. She clung to her horse’s wide neck, and his deep brown eyes brought
the only color and shadow of life into a void of energy.</p>

<p>So he ran, his hair whipping back behind him in a wind that should have been
soothing—instead it chilled his core, instilling him a frightened sense of
dread and loss. What was he supposed to be protecting? As he raced toward the
unknown center of iciness, what could he be sacrificing? His normally bright
blue eyes, filled with such life, were instead consumed by the black pupils, a
thin ring of ice coating a black pool of onyx. Still he ran, soundless, like a
fleeting memory.</p>

<p>The gray trees thinned and opened out onto a grand lake, a medieval stone castle
at its center. Walls ran around the castle, forming protective rings against
invasion. But it could not stop the cold. She sat atop her horse, he hoping she
wouldn’t do anything so daring and foolish, she wondering if the ice was thick
enough to hold her. She’d found herself in this strange place after falling
asleep—she might as well explore it. As she climbed down off her perch, he
whinnied gently. <em>Caution</em>.</p>

<p>A single crack pierced the still air and instantly he came to a halt, still as a
statue amongst leaves frozen in time and space. He looked up to find gray-white
stars winking out, thick clouds covering the spaces from where they had once
shined life down. A blur of white vapor breezed out of his mouth before catching
in the air and freezing like everything else around him. With the stars leaving,
the color drained, the life gone, he was lost amid a world of strange things
discovered in a daydream. But he knew, somewhere deep within the vibrations of
his abdomen he knew: he had to keep running. Faster and faster, like a shade of
the night. If only he could fly. He was afraid he’d be too late, but for what he
didn’t know.</p>

<p>She was stuck. The ice had started to creak after she’d made it about halfway
out to the castle. She was cursing her luck and hoping to progress without
further trouble when the cracks began to form, small at first but then more and
more concerning. She couldn’t move for fear of causing the whole shelf to
collapse at once and send her plunging into the frigid waters. Her brave horse
stood on the far bank, fear coursing through his eyes. He reared and whinnied
again, but this time no sound came out.</p>

<p>He burst through the trees, skidding to a halt in some kind of white slush as he
took in the scene before him. A young lonely girl stood helplessly amid the ice,
poised as though headed towards the looming castle before her. A horse stood on
the bank, terrified for the girl. And he, at the top of a hill, could see no
safe way to reach her. She turned around and locked eyes with him, and at that
moment the ice gave way and she fell.</p>

<p>She gasped at the shock the frigid water and it poured into her mouth, driving
any fight she had from her. She had thought the world could not be darker, but
the blackness edging her vision away was evidence to the contrary. Things were
disappearing fast, and her heavy arms would not move in the slowness of her
thoughts.</p>

<p>He was caught in a moment of irrational and torturous slowness. Eternity dragged
on as he watched the last glimpse of her pale hand dip below the surface. What
could he possibly do except fall in himself? He collapsed to his knees, a single
tear rolling onto the sleet beneath him.</p>

<p>A single ray of light pierced the cloud cover overhead. He felt lightheaded at
the irony—such sadness coupled with an unexpected shaft of optimism. And then
he realized he wasn’t just feeling lightheaded. He was actually floating off the
ground. Instincts kicked in as he soared high above the clouds. But wait: what
about the girl and her horse? Could he still save her? Was there still time? He
dived and the wind roared by his ears, the only sound echoing off the mountains
and giving the impression of thunder.</p>

<p>Something sparkled in the last dot of her vision. Something blue, maybe
blonde…oh well. Her eyes drifted shut.</p>

<p>When his hand thrust through the water, his vision reeled and everything
flipped. Suddenly he was reaching up from the sky into an ice-filled ocean
towards a girl up above him. He pulled her down to him into a now-cloudless sky.</p>

<hr />

<p>She awoke in paradise, staring at the blue eyes of some boy who had apparently
rescued her. She tried to sit up, but a blinding headache knocked her down. A
concerned look flitted across his face. No words passed between the two, because
the sound was still off, but language was an unnecessary barrier at this point.
A link forged in the icy steel of the lake existed between them.</p>

<p>Her horse wandered over and licked her cheek, a gentle reminder. The young man
who had saved her flashed a foolish grin at her, and when something slightly
more painful crowded his eyes she immediately wanted to comfort him. But the
horse nuzzled her again. He nodded. <em>Go on</em>. When he realized she could barely
stand on her own, he took her in his arms with a reflective expression on his
face. They drifted over the horses back and he set her down. He caressed her
cheek, but he did not cry. Not now. He looked at the horse, and something passed
between them. He was flooded by the image of a curly-haired young man, a man of
brown eyes and brown hair whose arms stood protectively around the girl atop his
back. The blonde man nodded. <em>Take care of her</em>. And he turned away as they
galloped into the forest.</p>

<hr />

<p>He was skimming through the air, admiring the returned stars and occasionally
just drifting as his mind wandered back to that strange day. He carried
something heavy in his heart, and it dragged him down.</p>

<p>Just then, it began to snow, soft flakes of ice buzzing by in flurries. The
pretty ice crystals danced and whirled in intricate patterns, caressing his
body. And suddenly he realized that his dead land of gray was actually beautiful
for the cold ice it contained and the life which it sustained in the radiant
glory of snowflakes and sunshine and stars—the reflections across thousands of
fragmented surfaces painted a glimmering beacon of hope among the snow-capped
mountains, and his heart soared and leapt with joy as he let go of a burden and
joined the stars in their colorful triumph.</p>]]></content><author><name>D. Ben Knoble</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Another piece for a close friend.]]></summary></entry></feed>